

# João de Jesus Costa

Software Engineer

Santa Maria da Feira, Portugal



+351 912768196



joaocosta.dev



jobs@joaocosta.dev



www.linkedin.com/in/joaocostaifg



github.com/JoaoCostaIFG

## About me -

I'm a software engineer with a Master's in Informatics Engineering. I like to develop personal software projects, take care of my servers, and write on my blog.

## Skills -

C - C++

Linux

Python

Docker

lava

JavaScript - TypeScript

Language skills -

Portuguese Native

English C1

Soft skills —

problem-solving flexibility communication

#### Bio

I like working in almost everything software related. I have a somewhat odd mix of work experiences, but my longest held positions mainly focused on embedded software development and safety-critical systems.

I get most of my knowledge/experience from personal projects outside of work. These projects involve informatics and electronics, spanning the whole tech stack. I'm also a big fan of open-source software and try to contribute to it as much as I can.

In my free time, you can find me working on personal projects, reading, or playing video games. I'm also a big fan of paintball and cycling.

#### Education

2021 - 2023 Master in Informatics Engineering
Final grade 18/20

2018 - 2021 Bachelor of Science
Final grade 18/20

Faculty of Engineering of the University of Porto (FEUP)
Faculty of Engineering of the University of Porto (FEUP)

#### Work experience

2024-present **Software Engineer** 

Synopsys

Software Engineer developing tools and CI/CD pipelines to support the development of drivers for baremetal systems.

Tech: C, Python, Bash

2024 Backend Software Engineer

Codacy

Backend Software Engineer working on a new security-focused product of the company. Worked mostly with Scala code-bases. Tasks included migrating parts of old backend components, implementing new endpoints, and refactoring databases.

Tech: Scala, Java, React

2022-2024 Embedded Software Engineer

Critical Software

Embedded Software Engineer working on the verification and validation of operating systems for the aerospace industry. Responsible for writing requirements, test cases, and test procedures on a team of 20 people.

Tools C. Assess ACNA

Tech: C, Arm ASM

2023-2024 Software Engineer

2022

Civil Engineering Department of FEUP

Solo freelancer work developing monitoring tools and pipelines for construction work that was taking place in the metro tunnels of the city of Porto. The objective was to acquire and process real-time sensor data and guarantee the safety of the workers

and the historical buildings in the area.

Software Engineer Intern

Critical Software

Internship program at Critical Software, with the objective of learning more about the company's activities, agile methodologies, and developing soft-skills.

Tech: Python, Java

Tech: Python, C#

2020-2021 Web Game Developer

children

LusoInfo

Member of a 4 people freelancer team tasked with porting a collection of flash games to the Unity game engine. The games are part of an educational game suite for school

Tech: C#, Unity



# João de Jesus Costa

### **Software Engineer**

Santa Maria da Feira, Portugal



+351 912768196



joaocosta.dev



jobs@joaocosta.dev



www.linkedin.com/in/joaocostaifg



github.com/JoaoCostaIFG

## About me -

I'm a software engineer with a Master's in Informatics Engineering. I like to develop personal software projects, take care of my servers, and write on my blog.

## Skills –

C - C++

Linux

Python

Docker

Java

JavaScript - TypeScript

#### Language skills -

Native Portuguese

**English C1** 

Soft skills —

problem-solving flexibility communication

#### **Awards**

2023 2nd place on AI for banking competition from Millennium

2018 University scholarship from Amorim Cork Composites

2018 Highest grade in informatics from highschool

#### **Projects**

2023 Octree implementation for SLAM Project's GitHub page

An Octree implementation in C++ for use in SLAM application for an autonomous submarine. This project was developed for the university's robotics research institute. The objective was improving the performance of existing Octree implementations for the current application without compromising the spatial efficiency and accuracy.

2022 TraSMAPv Project's GitHub page

A Python API for the SUMO traffic simulator with the objective of allowing researchers with limited knowledge in informatics and programming to model road traffic simulations. The API abstracts lower level concepts of the simulator and builds new concepts to make it easier to build agent-based simulations,

2022 μKernel Project's GitHub page

A real-time micro-kernel for the Arduino UNO supporting POSIX style tasks, mutexes, EDF scheduling, task sleeping, and assertions. Responsible for most of the implementation and research for the project.

2021 **Dry Beans classification**  Project's GitHub page

Model (unsupervised learning) to classify beans between seven classes with similar features. This served as an opportunity to gain experience in data science and machine learning libraries for python. Responsible for part of the data analysis and treatment, the application of unsupervised learning algorithms, and the comparison

of the results.

2021 **Segmentation Fault**  Project's GitHub page

Online QA web application resembling StackOverflow. This project was developed with the purpose of learning Bootstrap, Docker, Laravel, and PostgreSQL. Responsible for the Docker image, database design and indexes, most of the front-end, and accessibility/design choices.

2020-2021 MAWW

Project's GitHub page

Program that allows users (using X11) on Linux to have animated backgrounds, regardless of their compositor. This project is available as an Arch Linux package on the AUR.

#### **Publications**

Verification of real-time operating system for DO-178C compliance 2023

> My Master's thesis. The objective of my thesis was to analyze and optimize the processes of the aviation real-time OS verification team at Critical Software. This work resulted in several internal tools and optimizations that streamlined the development and saved money.